<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mar-Martin</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07045</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17461.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108323</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843984</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843984</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8760</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07045)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 894:10, 1731:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mar-Martin</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A tract in the Martin Marprelate controversy.</note>
                  <note>In verse. First line: I knowe not why a frutelesse lye in print;.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A² .</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 17462a on UMI microfilm reel 894.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 894 and at reel 1731 (same copy filmed twice).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marprelate controversy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:8760:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8760:1"/>
            <head>Mar-Martin.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Knowe not why a fruteleſſe lye in Print;</l>
               <l>May not aſwell with modeſtie be touched</l>
               <l>As truthleſſe Proſe, ſince neither hath his ſtint,</l>
               <l>And others dooings cannot be anouched:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then if both Rime and Proſe impugne the troth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>How lyke you him, lykes neyther of them both.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our Prelats (<hi>Martin</hi> ſayth) want skill and reaſon,</l>
               <l>Our Martiniſts <hi>Mar-martine</hi> tearmeth aſſes,</l>
               <l>The one an other doth accuſe of treaſon,</l>
               <l>He paſſeth beſt that by the gallowes paſſes.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Traytor, no Traytor, heeres ſuch Traytrous ſtriuing,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That Romiſh Traytors now are ſet a thriuing.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whileſt <hi>England</hi> falles a makening and marring,</l>
               <l>Reli<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion feares an vtter ouerthrowe,</l>
               <l>Whilſt we at home amongſt our ſelues are iarring,</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſeedes takes roote, which forrayne ſeedmen ſowe:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If this be true, as true it is for certayne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wo woorth</hi> Martin Mar-Prelat, <hi>and</hi> Mar-Martin.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:8760:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8760:2"/>
            <head>MAR-MARTIN.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N Whitſon euen laſt at night,</l>
               <l>I dreaming ſaw a prettie ſight,</l>
               <l>Three Menſters in a halter tyde,</l>
               <l>And one before who ſeemd their guide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>This formoſt lookt and lookt agayne,</l>
               <l>As if he had not all his trayne.</l>
               <l>With that I aſkt this gaping man</l>
               <l>His name: my name (quoth he) is <hi>Lucyan,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This is a <hi>Ieſuite</hi> (quoth he)</l>
               <l>This <hi>Martin</hi> and <hi>Mar-Martin</hi> be,</l>
               <l>I ſeeke but now for <hi>Macheuell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And roundly then we goe to Hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Two Bookes vpon a Table lay,</l>
               <l>For which two yonkers went to play,</l>
               <l>They tripe a Dye and thus did make,</l>
               <l>Who threwe the moſt ſhould both Bookes take.</l>
               <l>He that had <hi>Martin</hi> ſlang the firſt,</l>
               <l>An aſſe it was, which was the woorſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mar-Martins</hi> maiſter in the haſte,</l>
               <l>Hopt then to hit a better caſt,</l>
               <l>And yet as cunning as he was,</l>
               <l>He could not flyng aboue an aſſe.</l>
               <l>To geather by the eares they goe,</l>
               <l>Which of the aſſes got the throwe,</l>
               <l>The firſt vpon his aſſe would ſtand,</l>
               <l>He wan it by the elder hand.</l>
               <l>Tuſh quoth the ſecond that no matter,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8760:3"/>
Mine was an aſſe though twere the latter,</l>
               <l>And turning back, he ſpake to me,</l>
               <l>Who all this while this ſport did ſee,</l>
               <l>Iſt not a wonder, ſay of loue,</l>
               <l>That none of vs ſhould flyng aboue:</l>
               <l>No quoth I it were a wonder</l>
               <l>If eyther of you two had throwne vnder.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What ſons: what fathers: ſons and fathers fighting:</l>
               <l>Alas our welfare, and alas our health,</l>
               <l>What motes, what beames, &amp; both diſplayd in writing:</l>
               <l>Alas the Church, alas the common wealth.</l>
               <l>What at this time: what vnder ſuch a Queene:</l>
               <l>Alas that ſtill our frute ſhould be ſo greene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What wanton Calues: what loſt out former loue:</l>
               <l>Alas our pride, alas our mutabilitie,</l>
               <l>What Chriſt at oddes: what ſerpents ner adoue:</l>
               <l>Alas our rage, alas our inhumilitie.</l>
               <l>What bitter ta<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>s, what lyes in ſtead of preaching,</l>
               <l>Alas our health, alas our neede of teaching.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beare gratious Soueraigne, <hi>Europs</hi> matchles mirror,</l>
               <l>Beare noble Lords renowined counſell geuers,</l>
               <l>Beare Cleargie men, for yours is all the error,</l>
               <l>Beare common people, common light beleeuers.</l>
               <l>Beare ioyntly one anothers weakeneſſe ſo,</l>
               <l>That though we wither, yet the Church may growe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If all be true that Lawyers ſay,</l>
               <l>The ſecond blowe doth make the fray,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mar-Mrtins</hi> fault can be no leſſe</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Martins</hi> was that brake the peace.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Martin, Mar-Martine, Barrowe</hi> and <hi>Browne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All helpe to pull Religion downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8760:3"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
